Guide to the Thomas Campbell papers, 1807-1843 MS 140
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Thomas Campbell papers
1807-1843
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Campbell, Thomas
MS 140
0.1 Linear Feet (1 folder)
The collection includes letters from, portraits, autographs, and a drawing of, a fragment of a poem by, and an article written by Thomas Campbell, as well as biographical information about Campbell and Alfred Tennyson.
Biographical Note
Thomas Campbell, a Scottish poet, was born July 27, 1777 in Glasgow. His published volumes include "Pleasures of Hope" in 1799, "Gertrude of Wyoming" in 1809, and Theodric in 1834. He is best known for his war poems, such as "Hohenlinden," "The Battle of the Baltic," and "Ye Mariners of England."
By 1805 he was employed at the Star newspaper. In 1820, he became editor for "The New Monthly Magazine." In 1825, he suggested the London University, playing a large part in its founding, and in 1827 was elected rector of Glasgow University.
Thomas Campbell passed away on June 15, 1844 at Boulogne, and was buried at Westminster Abbey.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes "Notices of the Life of Lord Byron by Moore and Remarks on Those Notices by Lady Byron", part of an article which poet Campbell published in "The New Monthly Magazine," in March or April, 1830 decrying Moore's biography of Byron and defending Lady Byron in the matter of the couple's separation. Also included is a signed receipt (1843, "Payment for fourth copy of my Poems".) and letters to Francis Freeling, J. Richardson, Miller, Engraver at Edinburgh and others. They describe a holiday in the Isle of Wight, in one he writes about postage on his sheets from the printer; in others he discusses his writings. There is also a portrait of Campbell in the collection.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Myers (dealer).
Index Terms
Subjects
Poetry; Literature
Document Types
corrrespondence; articles
Subjects (Persons)
Byron, George Gordon Byron, Baron; Campbell, Thomas
- Series I: Correspondence and poem fragment, 1807-1843, 11095
  - Letter from Thomas Campbell to J. Richardson, June, 1807, 11109 (Folder 1)
  - Letter from Thomas Campbell to unknown, January 17, 1817, 11108 (Folder 1)
  - Letter from Thomas Campbell to unknown, November 28, 1818, 11107 (Folder 1)
  - Letter from Thomas Campbell to Francis Feeling, October 20, 1824, 11106 (Folder 1)
  - Letter from Thomas Campbell to Francis Feeling, November 25, 1826, 11105 (Folder 1)
  - Letter from Thomas Campbell to unknown, May 13, 1828, 11104 (Folder 1)
  - "Notices on the Life of Lord Byron by Moore and Remarks on Those Notices by Lady Byron," article from The New Monthly by Thomas Campbell, March-April 1830 (incomplete), 11103 (Folder 1)
  - Fragment of poem entitled "Hallowed Ground" by Thomas Campbell, attatched to paper with commentary by Carline Fox, ca. 1835, 11102 (Folder 1)
  - Letter from Thomas Campbell to unknown, April 18, 1837, 11101 (Folder 1)
  - Letter from Thomas Campbell to Mr. Miller (Engraver), April 24, 1837, 11100 (Folder 1)
  - Letter from Thomas Campbell tp unknown, June 20, 1837, 11099 (Folder 1)
  - Letter from Thomas Campbell to unknown, July 21, 1840, 11098 (Folder 1)
  - Receipt from Thomas Campbell acknowledging payment for poems by P. Buckley Williams, April 8, 1843, 11097 (Folder 1)
  - Letter from Thomas Campbell to unknown ("Johnny") including short tune, n.d., 11096 (Folder 1)
- Series II: Portraits, drawings, and autographs, undated, 11090
  - Portrait of Thomas Campbell, n.d., 11094 (Folder 1)
  - Drawing by (or of) Thomas Campbell, n.d., 11093 (Folder 1)
  - Portrait of Thomas Campbell and Autograph, n.d., 11092 (Folder 1)
  - Autographs of Thomas Campbell and Biographical Information about Campbell and Alfred Tennyson, n.d. (sometime after 1872), 11091 (Folder 1)